A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Office Files of Henry T. Heald FA622
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of the President, Office Files of Henry T. Heald
1956-1966
Rockefeller Archive Center
Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley)
Ford Foundation
FA622
5.28 Cubic Feet
The office files of Henry T. Heald cover the years 1951, and 1956 to 1966, and consist of correspondence and reports. They are arranged into one series: Subject Files. Arrangement within the series corresponds as closely as possible to the original order established by Heald's office.
Biographical / Historical
Henry T. Heald was President of the Ford Foundation from 1956 to 1965.
Dr. Heald was born November 8, 1904 in Lincoln, Nebraska. He received his B.S. degree in 1923 from Washington State College, and his M.S. degree in 1925 from the University of Illinois, both in civil engineering. In 1942, he earned the D.Eng. degree from the Rose Polytechnic Institute, and the LL.D. from Northwestern University. Mr. Heald was awarded more than twenty honorary doctoral degrees.
Prior to Heald's career with the Ford Foundation, he was associated with the Armour Institute of Technology from 1927 until 1940. During this period, Heald rose from the rank of Assistant Professor of Civil Engineering to Professor and Dean of the College. In 1940, Mr. Heald was instrumental in bringing about the consolidation of the Armour Institute with the Lewis Institute to form the Illinois Institute of Technology, where he served as President until 1952. From 1952 until 1956, Heald served as Chancellor (President) of New York University.
Following his retirement from the Foundation, Heald served as a consultant to the Case Institute of Technology and the Western Reserve University to establish the Case Western Reserve University of Cleveland, Ohio.
Henry T. Heald died November 23, 1975 in Winter Park, Florida.
Scope and Contents
The office files of Henry T. Heald consist of 15 linear feet (12 archives boxes) of correspondence and reports. They are concerned with the organization and operation of the Ford Foundation during the years 1951 and 1956-1966.
Areas in which pers provide useful background information include the material on the Trustee Building Committee (box 11, folders 143-146) and the so-called Patman Committee (box 8, folders 102-105). For the building committee, the papers include correspondence and reports between Board members and other Foundation officers, with regard to the construction of new Foundation headquarters on East 43rd Street. The Foundation moved into its new building in November 1967. Included are the initial proposals made by five architectural firms. C. Wright Patman, Chairman of the House of Representatives' House Select Committee on Small Business, Subcommittee Number One on Foundations, held hearings on tax-exempt foundations in 1964 and 1967. The Committee was concerned with the way private philanthropies were regulated, or should be regulated, by the Federal tax system and their place in the economy in general. The Patman Committee material provides the researcher with substantive correspondence regarding the implications of the hearings for the Ford Foundation, as well as for philanthrophy in general.
The remainder of the records, while broad in scope, lack significant depth and consist of topics covered in a basic manner. The primary value of the papers is the overview they provide of the interests and concerns of the Ford Foundation and its president during the period of the mid-fifties to the mid-sixties.
Arrangement
The Office of the President Files of Henry T. Heald are organized as a single series, Subject Files, and are arranged alphabetically by subject, then chronologically within each subject category.
Separated Materials
Reports and publications were transferred to their respective collections in the Archives. Transfers are noted on cross-reference sheets in Heald's records. An appendix to this register lists reports transferred to the Archives' Reports Collection. Papers not related to Ford Foundation activities have been removed.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files and officers papers were transferred to, and accessioned by, RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
- Subject Files, I
  - Aging, Problems of the, 1957 April - 1961 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Annual Reports, 1956 October - 1965 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Argentina-Chile, 1958 May - 1965 October (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles of Incorporation and By-laws, 1956 September - 1957 August (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Atwater, Verne, 1956 November - 1965 November (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Audit Committee Meetings, 1956 November - 1964 December (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Balance of Payments, 1965 March - 1962 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brazil, 1959 January - 1964 January (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Budget 1959-1960, 1959 - 1959 June (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Budget 1960-1961, 1960 - 1960 July (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Budget 1961-1962, 1961 - 1962 March (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Budget 1962-1963, 1961 December - 1962 September (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Budget 1963-1964, 1962 November - 1963 September (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Budget 1964-1965, 1964 February - 1964 October (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Budget 1965-1966, 1965 February - December (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Burma, 1960 November - 1962 June (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Car and Driver, 1958 December - 1965 July (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Caribbean, 1959 August - 1964 November (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Citizen's Committee for International Development, 1961 July - October (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Colombia-Venezula, 1959 November - 1964 March (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Comptroller, 1956 December - 1963 February (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Comptroller, 1963 March - 1965 December (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Conflict of Interest, 1961 April - 1965 December (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Council on Library Resources, 1956 June - July; 1958 October - 1965 December (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Cuba, 1960 January; 1961 February - March (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Delegation of Authority, 1957 July - 1965 July (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Economic Development and Administration, 1956 July - 1958 November (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Economic Development and Administration, 1959 January - 1965 June (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Education - Graduate, 1959 July - September (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Education - Journalism, 1963 July - 1964 October (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Education - Negro, 1963 July - 1964 October (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Education - Special Programs in Liberal Arts Colleges, 1960 November - 1964 February (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Education - Special Programs in Universities, 1959 July - 1965 August (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Education - V.P. Faust, 1956 October - 1959 February (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Education - V.P. Faust, 1959 April - 1965 June (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Education - Vocational, 1962 June - 1963 September (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - Educational Facilities Laboratories, 1957 January - 1965 December (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Educational Television - General, 1959 September - 1960 January (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Educational Television - General, 1961 January - 1965 December (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Endowment Grants, 1964 October - 1965 January (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Ethiopia, 1958 April - July (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Exchange of Persons, 1958 December - 1961 January (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Finance Committee, 1955 September - 1958 March (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Finance Committee, 1958 May - 1960 January (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Finance Committee, 1960 February - 1965 October (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Foundation Library Center, 1957 January - 1965 October (Box 3, Folder 46)
  - Ford Motor Company - Correspondence, 1956 December - 1959 August (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Ford Motor Company - Correspondence, 1959 September - 1960 December (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Ford Motor Company - Correspondence, 1961 January - 1962 June (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Ford Motor Company - Correspondence, 1962 July - November (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Ford Motor Company - Correspondence, 1962 November - 1964 October (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Ford Motor Company – Correspondence, 1964 October - 1965 October (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Ford Motor Company - Sale of Stock, 1959 January - December (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Ford Motor Company - Sale of Stock, 1959 December - 1965 September (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Free World Economic Cooperation - Staff Ad Hoc Committee on, 1958 July - November (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Fund for Adult Education, 1956 October - 1959 December (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Fund for Adult Education, 1960 January - 1965 December (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Fund for the Advancement of Education, 1956 October - 1963 July (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Fund for the Republic, 1957 January - 1959 November (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Fund for the Republic, 1960 February - 1963 February (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - General Counsel, 1954 November - 1964 July (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Ghana, 1958 July - 1964 February (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Humanities and the Arts, 1956 October 8 - 1959 May 28 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Humanities and the Arts, 1959 July - 1965 October (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - India, 1956 September - 1958 December (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - India, 1959 January - 1961 July (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - India, 1961 September - 1965 December (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - Indonesia, 1956 July - 1965 October (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - Institute for Advanced Studies in the Behavioral Sciences, 1956 October - 1964 November (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - International Affairs, 1956 November - 1962 December (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - International Affairs, 1963 February - 1965 November (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - International Programs, 1961 October - 1965 November (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - International Training and Research, 1956 November - 1959 July (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - International Training and Research, 1959 August - 1961 April (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - International Training and Research, 1961 May - 1965 November (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Japan, 1959 January - 1965 January (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Katz, Milton, 1951 July - 1957 November (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Katz, Milton, 1957 December - 1960 May (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - Katz, Milton, 1960 August - 1963 September (Box 6, Folder 79)
  - Katz, Milton, 1963 December - 1965 September (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - Kenya, 1963 December; 1965 March - April (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Latin America, 1958 May - 1965 November (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - Lebanon-Syria, 1956 October - 1965 September (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Library, 1958 June - 1965 May (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Lincoln Center, 1956 February - 1965 December (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Malaysia, 1962 March - June; 1964 December - 1965 July (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Memoranda - Heald's, 1956 December - 1965 October (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - Mexico-Central America, 1958 May - 1964 October (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Michigan Philanthropies, 1956 October - 1964 September (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - Middle East and Africa, 1956 November - 1965 July (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - National Achievement Scholorship Program, 1964 July - November (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - NASA, 1959 May - 1965 August (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - National Humanities Foundation, 1957 February - 1965 March (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - National Merit Scholarship Corporation, 1957 October - 1964 August (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Nepal, 1957 September - 1959 November (Box 7, Folder 95)
  - New York State Regulation of Charitable Organizations, 1965 December (Box 7, Folder 96)
  - Nigeria, 1958 September - 1965 September (Box 7, Folder 97)
  - Overseas Development, 1956 September - 1959 May (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Overseas Development, 1959 June - 1963 July (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - Overseas Development, 1963 August - July (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Pakistan, 1956 October - 1965 September (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - Patman Committee, 1955 September - 1962 December (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Patman Committee, 1963 January - December (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - Patman Committee, 1964 January - July (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Patman Committee, 1964 August - 1965 April (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Personnel, Recruitment of, 1963 May - 1965 September (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Peru, 1959 December; 1961 December - 1962 January (Box 9, Folder 107)
  - Philanthropy, 1955 June - 1964 July (Box 9, Folder 108)
  - Philippines, 1963 November - 1964 December (Box 9, Folder 109)
  - Policy and Planning, 1956 December - 1964 December (Box 9, Folder 110)
  - Policy and Planning, 1965 February - December (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - Population, 1956 November - 1965 July (Box 9, Folder 112)
  - President's Commission on Education (Beyond High School), 1956 November - 1957 April (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - President's Commission on National Goals, 1959 March - 1961 June (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - Public Affairs, 1956 August - 1958 September (Box 9, Folder 115)
  - Public Affairs, 1958 November - 1964 February (Box 9, Folder 116)
  - Public Affairs, 1964 March - 1965 November (Box 9, Folder 117)
  - Puerto Rico, 1959 January - October (Box 9, Folder 118)
  - Records Manager, 1957 March - 1964 July (Box 9, Folder 119)
  - Refugees, 1956 December - 1959 April (Box 9, Folder 120)
  - Research and Statistics, 1956 November - 1965 November (Box 9, Folder 121)
  - Resources and the Environment, 1964 February - 1965 August (Box 9, Folder 122)
  - Resources for the Future, 1956 November - 1965 April (Box 9, Folder 123)
  - Russia, 1957 May - 1963 August (Box 9, Folder 124)
  - Salary Committee, 1962 May - 1965 May (Box 10, Folder 125)
  - Science and Engineering, 1955 November - 1965 August (Box 10, Folder 126)
  - Secretary, Office of, 1956 October - 1960 September (Box 10, Folder 127)
  - Secretary, Office of, 1960 October - 1965 October (Box 10, Folder 128)
  - Small Grants, 1956 August - 1957 February (Box 10, Folder 129)
  - South and SE Asia, 1958 July - 1965 August (Box 10, Folder 130)
  - Special Programs, Ad Hoc Committee on, 1959 March - 1962 September (Box 10, Folder 131)
  - Statement - Principles and Practices, 1964 August - October (Box 10, Folder 132)
  - Statistical Information, 1962 April - 1964 June (Box 10, Folder 133)
  - Survey of Administrative Organization, 1964 April - August (Box 10, Folder 134)
  - Television-Radio Workshop, 1956 October - 1960 November (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Thailand, 1961 November - 1965 June (Box 10, Folder 136)
  - Travel and Study Program, 1964 December - 1965 March (Box 10, Folder 137)
  - Treasurer, 1955 September - 1958 August (Box 10, Folder 138)
  - Treasurer, 1958 October - 1960 September (Box 11, Folder 139)
  - Treasurer, 1960 October - 1965 April (Box 11, Folder 140)
  - Trustee Ad Hoc Committee on Development Program, 1962 August - 1963 March (Box 11, Folder 141)
  - Trustee Ad Hoc Committee on Personnel for International Activities, 1962 March - 1963 March (Box 11, Folder 142)
  - Trustee Building Committee, 1961 April - 1963 May (Box 11, Folder 143)
  - Trustee Building Committee, 1963 May - 1964 March (Box 11, Folder 144)
  - Trustee Building Committee, 1964 March - December (Box 11, Folder 145)
  - Trustee Building Committee, 1965 January - December (Box 11, Folder 146)
  - Tunisia, 1961 September - 1965 September (Box 12, Folder 147)
  - Turkey, 1960 January - 1965 February (Box 12, Folder 148)
  - United Arab Republic, 1959 November - 1965 May (Box 12, Folder 149)
  - U.S. Government, 1956 November - 1960 June (Box 12, Folder 150)
  - U.S. Government, 1960 June - 1963 December (Box 12, Folder 151)
  - U.S. Government, 1963 December - 1965 December (Box 12, Folder 152)
  - U.S. Government – Health, Education and Welfare, 1956 August - 1964 July (Box 12, Folder 153)
  - U.S. Government Treasury Department, 1964 November - 1965 October (Box 12, Folder 154)
  - Urban Redevelopment, 1958 February - 1965 April (Box 12, Folder 155)
  - Woodrow Wilson Fellowship Corporation, 1957 January - 1965 December (Box 12, Folder 156)
  - Youth Development, 1957 February - 1963 February (Box 12, Folder 157)